Mss.B.Sm59
American Philosophical Society
J. Russell (Joseph Russell) Smith papers, [ca. 1888]-1966
Circa 1888-1966
Mss.B.Sm59
American Philosophical Society
11.0 Linear feet
Ca. 11,000 items.
A collection of letters (family and professional), notebooks, diaries, lectures, articles, and photographs, of Smith, a noted American geographer who influenced the teaching of geography after 1920 through his many elementary texts. There is much material relating to these writings. His contributions to the rise of human geography and the related areas of conservation and ecology, are documented. His study in Europe under Friedrich Ratzel, at Leipzig in 1901-1912, is touched on in his journal for those years; included are many interesting observations on German university life. There is also much material on his nursery business in Virginia. Organizational files are numerous, e.g. Association of American Geographers, Columbia University, U. S. Department of Agriculture. Much of the correspondence is limited to only a few letters from each correspondent. Among the names included are: Willard G. Bixby, Isaiah Bowman, John W. Hershey, Emory R. Johnson, Walter C. Lowdermilk (of particular note is his 1926 paper, written while at the University of Nanking, "Forest Conservation in Shansi, China"), and Lewis Mumford.
Smith, J. Russell, (Joseph Russell), 1874-1966
Box 1-22
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by the Smith family and accessioned, 10/--/1966 (1966 2120ms).
Biographical/Historical note
J. Russell Smith was a geographer who influenced the teaching of geography after 1920 through his many elementary texts.
Association of American Geographers.; Bixby, Willard G.; Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950; Columbia University -- Faculty.; Hershey, John W.; Johnson, Emory Richard, 1864-1950; Lowdermilk, W. C., (Walter Clay), 1888-1974; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Ratzel, Friedrich, 1844-1904; United States. -- Dept. of Agriculture.; Articles.; Conservation of natural resources.; Diaries.; Ecology.; Forest conservation -- China -- Shanxi Sheng.; Geography -- Societies, etc.; Geography.; Germany -- Universities and colleges.; Human geography.; Lectures.; Notebooks.; Nurseries (Horticulture) -- Virginia.; Photoprints.
- Photographs, 16.0 Photograph(s); This collection represents a sample of the photographs available in the J. Russel Smith papers.
  - Joseph Russell Smith at a young age, n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Carte de visite of Smith at a young age.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, formal portrait, ca. 1890; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of Smith.
  - Abington Friends School, group portrait, 1892., 1.0 Photograph(s); Eleven school-age boys sitting outside on ground, wood pile in background. Smith is second to right, back row.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, formal portrait with beard, ca. 1898; Formal portrait of Smith with beard.
    General note
    Handwritten note on back of photograph: "Taken before Jan. 1899."
  - Joseph Russell Smith and Henrietta S. Smith in their room at George School, 1898, 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of the Smiths, seated in room.
  - Joseph Russell Smith and Henrietta Stewart Smith, 1902, 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal group photo of Joseph and Henrietta Smith.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, mounted photograph, 1908, 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal 3/4 view portrait of Smith.
  - Northern Nut Growers' Association group portait, 1916, 1916 September; 1.0 Photograph(s); Group portrait of officers of the Northern Nut Grower's Association, Washington, D. C.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, seated at table in Okaya, Japan, 1925, 1925 August 30; 1.0 Photograph(s); Group portrait of Smith and eight people, sitting and standing, at table.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, with unidentified men, Japan, 1925, 1.0 Photograph(s); Group portrait with Smith, seated in center, and seven unidentified men.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, seated outside on bench, n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Smith, seated on bench, columns of building in background.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, standing outside examing plant, 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Smith examining plant.
  - Joselph Russell Smith and family, 1.0 Photograph(s); Group portrait of three generations of the Smith family.
  - Joselph Russell Smith, August 1942, 1942 August; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length portrait of Smith, standing outside on steps.
  - Joseph Russell Smith lecturing at Columbia University, n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Smith standing at desk in front of seated students, maps hanging in background.
  - Joseph Russell Smith, seated in boat, n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of Smith seated in foreground, two men, seated in back, without shirts rowing.